<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The inconsistencie of the independent way, with Scripture and it self. Manifested in a threefold discourse, I. Vindicia vindiciarum, with M. Cotton. II. A review of M. Hookers Survey of church-discipline. The first part. III. A diatribe with the same M. Hooker concerning baptism of infants of non-confederate parents, cap. 2. Of his third part. / By Daniel Cawdrey ...</title>
            <author>Cawdrey, Daniel, 1588-1664.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1651</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 45 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A78425</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C1629A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R22287</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12264390</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12264390</idno>
            <idno type="VID">171559</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A78425)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 171559)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 176:13 or 2568:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The inconsistencie of the independent way, with Scripture and it self. Manifested in a threefold discourse, I. Vindicia vindiciarum, with M. Cotton. II. A review of M. Hookers Survey of church-discipline. The first part. III. A diatribe with the same M. Hooker concerning baptism of infants of non-confederate parents, cap. 2. Of his third part. / By Daniel Cawdrey ...</title>
                  <author>Cawdrey, Daniel, 1588-1664.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[26], 219 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by A. Miller for Christopher Meredith at the Sign of the Crane in Pauls Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>MDCLI [1651]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Each of the three titles have separate title pages.</note>
                  <note>Errata: p. [24].</note>
                  <note>Marginal notes.</note>
                  <note>Item at reel 176:13 is a reproduction of original in Thomason Collection, British Library.</note>
                  <note>Item at reel 2568:13 is a reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
                  <note>Item at reel 176:13 is incorrectly identified as Wing C1629.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: item at reel 2568:13 is lacking all after p. [24].</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Cotton, John, 1584-1652. --  Way of Congregational churches cleared.</term>
               <term>Hooker, Thomas, 1586-1647. --  Survey of the summe of church-discipline.</term>
               <term>Congregational churches --  Controversial literature.</term>
               <term>Baptism --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Church polity.</term>
               <term>Church discipline.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:171559:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:171559:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE INCONSISTENCIE OF THE Independent way, With Scripture, and It Self.</p>
            <p>Manifeſted in a threefold Diſcourſe,
<list>
                  <item>I. <hi>Vindiciae Vindiciarum,</hi> with M. <hi>Cotton.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>II. <hi>A Review of</hi> M. <hi>Hookers Survey of Church-Diſcipline.</hi> The firſt part.</item>
                  <item>III. <hi>A Diatribe</hi> with the ſame M. <hi>Hooker Concerning Baptiſm of Infants of Non-confederate parents,</hi> Cap. 2. Of his third part.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>By DANIEL CAWDREY, a Member of the Aſſembly, and late Preacher at <hi>Martins</hi> in the Fields.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>JEREMY 6.16.</hi>
               </bibl> Stand ye in the waies, and ſee, and ask for the old paths, where is the good way, and walk therein, and ye ſhall finde reſt for your ſouls.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>A. Miller</hi> for <hi>Christopher Meredith</hi> at the Sign of the Crane in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard, MDCLI.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:171559:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:171559:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>THE EPISTLE TO THE Diſſenting Brethren.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is ſome mens happineſſe (I know not how or why, unleſſe it be out of the partiality of their <hi>Followers</hi> to their own way and party) that write they (or preach they) never ſo weakly (or abſurdly) they finde ſome admirers to cry them up, all their words as Oracles, and all their works as Wonders. Other men, though they do clearly diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver (perhaps becauſe they do diſcover) the weakneſſes and contradictions of thoſe waies and works, muſt have their Books buried in ſilence, ſlighted and ſcorn'd, or themſelves cenſured and traduced:
<note place="margin">Ep. to the Way cleared, pag. 2.</note> 
               <hi>[as carrying on a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign, endeavouring by pen to blot the fair Copy of Truth, and to croſse out of the Book of mens memory and eſteem, the names of them whom God will honour though they will not,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:171559:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>&amp;c.] I have obſerved it as a depth of Romiſh policy of late, That they have left off to anſwer to any contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted points (being beaten out of the field by the full and clear confutations of their Doctrines, by our late learned Champions) and betake themſelves now to a complyance with all Hereſies and Sects, ſo to oppreſſe the Truth in another way, by crying down both Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry and Learning. To which purpoſe, ſome Jeſuiticall Pamphlets have been vented of late in ſeverall dreſſes,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>The Swords Abuſe</hi> aſſerted. <hi>The vanity of the preſent Churches,</hi> &amp;c.</note> and ſcattered abroad to do miſchief, which have been anſwered and confuted; but they have the wit, not to reply, leſt they make the cauſe worſe. This practice ſome of our Independent Brethren have too much imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tated; Witneſſe the <hi>Diatribe,</hi> about Ordination, Impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of hands, and preaching by Gifted men, not in Office; which being learnedly and judiciouſly anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by D. <hi>S.</hi> and proved to be a <hi>Paradiatribe,</hi> the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thour thereof (thought to be a great man amongſt them) is unwilling (it ſeems) to reply, whether out of conſciouſneſſe of his own weakneſſe, or out of pride and ſcorn of all, not of his own way and opinion; that his Diſciples may think it is not worth anſwering. The like I may ſay of <hi>Vind. Clav.</hi> which having diſcovered many weakneſſes and contradictions in <hi>The Keys</hi> and <hi>Way,</hi> is anſwered rather with ſlighting and ſcorn, then any ſolid convictions, as will appear in this preſent <hi>Vindication.</hi> Of 7. Chapters in the <hi>Vind. Clav.</hi> he an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers but to one; and of 3. Sections in that firſt Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pter, he anſwers but to two; and throughout thoſe 2. Sections, doth rather reproach his adverſary by the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſerved names of <hi>Vindex</hi> and <hi>Avenger,</hi> then ſatisfie his charge. And after a threefold promiſe (with atte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtation of the Name of God twice) to give a further
<pb facs="tcp:171559:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>anſwer, ſhakes him off, as ſome contemptible perſon, ſet to be ſlighted, rather then anſwered. When I had, upon the firſt ſight of his book, read what he had writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, I preſently ſet pen to paper, and made a draught of this preſent <hi>Vindication;</hi> but yet was not perſwaded to print it, partly becauſe I waited till M. <hi>Baily</hi> and M. <hi>Rutherford</hi> put out their Reply, to joyn it with theirs, (which I have long in vain expected) and partly becauſe I was unwilling to make any further Diſcovery of the weakneſſes of the Reverend Authour, and partly becauſe I might think, the beſt anſwer to a ſlight anſwer, was no anſwer. But when I conſidered, that the Book was cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed up by the Epiſtler to it, as ſo exquiſite a piece; in theſe words: <hi>[In the latter part of this Book</hi> (The Way Cleared) <hi>being controverſal, you have a fair Additional to the Models afore printed of the Church-way (ſo much called for) not Magiſterially laid down, but friendly debated by Scripture, and argumentatively diſputed out, to the utmoſt inch of ground, and defended</hi> Cap a pie <hi>(as they ſpeak) from the head to the heel, of every branch of truth eſsentiall to the controverſie:]</hi> and when withall I perceived that this and other Books of that <hi>Way</hi> publiſhed, were highly e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteemed as unanſwerable, and very taking with weak and unſetled mindes, to the diſturbance of the peace of the Church; I found no reſt in my ſpirit till I had ſeriouſly tried the ſtrength thereof, eſpecially of that Reverend and Learned M. <hi>Hookers Survey of Church-Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline,</hi> which I heard moſt magnified, as the ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt piece of that <hi>Way;</hi> and ſo by the way give in a ſhort anſwer in Vindication of <hi>Vind. Clav.</hi> from the Reply of M. <hi>J. C.</hi> ſo far as concerned my ſelf.
<note place="margin">Ep. to the <hi>Way</hi> Ep. to the <hi>Way</hi> cleared.</note> To forward this undertaking, I was the rather provoked; 1. By the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunate and reiterated recognition of thoſe Tracts,
<pb facs="tcp:171559:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>thoſe <hi>Models</hi> (as they call them) <hi>of the Church-way,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ibid.</note> viz. <hi>Church-Government, Church-Covenant,</hi> &amp;c. and now the late <hi>Modell</hi> (or <hi>crambe ſaepe cocta</hi>) of M. <hi>Bartlet,</hi> and this Additional, of the <hi>Way Cleared.</hi> 2. By the often re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peated quarelling,
<note place="margin">Ep. to the <hi>Way</hi>
               </note> at our calling for a fuller Treatiſe, and a clearer Modell of the Church-way: 3. By the non-performance of that promiſe ſo long ago made, ſo often pretended, <hi>[Of a fuller Treatiſe of the ſame Subject, with ampler demonſtrations, by joint conſent of the Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es of Old and New England.]</hi> But will they never take notice of the Anſwers given to moſt, or many of thoſe? (for they all hold out the ſame things;) And why are they not rather offended (we have told them we are, and they ought to have given us ſatisfaction, had they eſteemed us brethren) offended, I ſay, at their own ſcandalous breach of promiſe, in not exhibiting that fuller Treatiſe by joint conſent, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Our Brethren of the Aſſembly, how long, how oft did they promiſe a full Modell of their <hi>Way,</hi> which yet we have as long and as oft called for, and expected, but all in vain? The time was, when ſome complained (but cauſeleſly) as an excuſe of their neglect of promiſe,
<note place="margin">Ep. to the <hi>Woy</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>[That their hands were bound up, and of the unwillingneſse of Licenſers to Licenſe their Tracts,</hi> &amp;c.] But ſure theſe laſt two or three years, their hands have been looſe enough, and the preſſe open; but ſtill this fuller Treatiſe by joint conſent, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> cannot finde the way into the Light: We have rather cauſe to think, that their diſagreement among them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, is the reaſon why they dare not give us their Model, leſt the world ſhould ſee their differences (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo few of them) and their Lightneſſe and Incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy, if (as oft they have done) they ſhould hereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter change their Judgements, upon pretence of New
<pb facs="tcp:171559:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>Light, perhaps as old errour, as that they left laſt.</p>
            <p>That I may briefly declare my judgement, concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this <hi>Way,</hi> ſo much adored and magnified by many; there are three things which have much prevailed with me, to perſwade me, that it is not the way of Chriſt.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The contradictions, at leaſt the many differences, as from the Scriptures, ſo from one another, and one man from himſelf; a Scheme whereof is preſented, at the end of our firſt part.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The propenſity of many of their principles (where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in they differ from the Presbyterians) to ſeparation, and to the worſt of Schiſm; I ſhall inſtance in ſome parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>[That there is no Catholike viſible Church, no Church viſible but a particular Congregation:]</hi> which is to deny all communion of Churches, and to grant only com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion of members; yea, ſome grant ſcarcely ſo much: Witneſs the Reverend Authour of the <hi>Survey of Church-Diſcipline,</hi> who ſaies expreſly,
<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Surv.</hi> par. 2. pag. 64, 65.</note> 
               <hi>[He hath profeſsed the courſe (of adminiſtration of the Sacrament to thoſe of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Congregation) to be unwarrantable; becauſe the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration of the Sacrament is a Ministerial Act, and what authority hath he (the Paſtor) to do it, or they to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive it from him to whom he is no Paſtor?]</hi> This muſt needs open a door to as many diviſions as there are Churches, none having any power beyond their own Church: whereby all Religions, all Hereſies, may be to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerated, and none can hinder it.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>That all Church-power, the power of the Keys, is inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendently and ſolely in a particular Congregation;]</hi> which is the ſetting up of Church againſt Church: and that Admiſſion and Ejection of members is only into and from a particular Church: A childe is baptized into a
<pb facs="tcp:171559:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>particular Congregation, and not into the Catholike, or other Churches, to them he is an Infidell: And one excommunicated is caſt out only of his particular Church, becauſe the power extends no further then to a particular Congregation.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>That a Church eſsentiall, or a Congregation of belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers without Officers, may chuſe and ordain her own Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers:]</hi> which will be the ready way to break them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſeparated Aſſemblies, one part chuſing one, another another.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>That a Miniſter is a Miniſter to none but his own Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation:]</hi> which tends to deſtroy the unity of the Church, and that communion which the Churches of God may and ought to have one with another.</p>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>Gathering of Churches out of true Churches;]</hi> which gives way to every man to ſeparate from his own, and to joyn himſelf with another Church, ſuppoſed purer; with contempt of the former Congregation: The Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verend M. <hi>Hooker</hi> confeſſeth;
<note place="margin">Praef. to his <hi>Survey,</hi> p. 11. &amp; in his Book.</note> 
               <hi>[That the faithful Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations in</hi> England <hi>are true Churches, and therefore it is ſinful to ſeparate from them as no Churches:]</hi> And yet our brethren here practiſe this ſeparation, by gathering their Churches out of ours, confeſſedly true Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches.</p>
            <p n="6">6. <hi>That none but confederates by the explicit Church-Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant have right to Ordinances:]</hi> which is to keep out many precious ſouls from communion with their fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low-members, and their children from Baptiſm, and to make them no better then Infidels. That's the ſecond thing.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The many miſchievous conſequences of thoſe principles, and ſad effects, of the practice of the Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendent way, in <hi>Old England,</hi> fully manifeſted in
<pb facs="tcp:171559:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>theſe few laſt years: For inſtance.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Under the Name, Shadow, and Shelter of Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendency (as another Trojan Horſe) have not only o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Sectaries, but had liberty to ſet up their Churches, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; but alſo the Jeſuites themſelves, have masked under this Vizard, transforming themſelves into all ſhapes and ſects; and have had the faireſt (or rather the fouleſt) opportunity to propagate all monſtrous and ſoul deſtroying errours; and to ruin not only the Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterian but the Independent Churches alſo: Evident it is, that moſt of the points of Popery, are preached and publiſhed in theſe Churches, as a fair inducement to uſher in the Antichriſtian Religion, whenever the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular power ſhall come into their hand.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Their Renouncing of their former Ordination in our Churches (which is reported to be done by ſome, if not moſt of our Diſſenting Brethren) hath miniſtred occaſion to Jeſuites, Anabaptiſts, profane perſons, and ſuch like, to cry down our Miniſtry, as Antichriſtian, or null: and hath expoſed us to all thoſe foul reproach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es of <hi>Baals</hi> Prieſts, Falſe Prophets, Black-coats, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which are daily poured out againſt the faithfull Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of Jeſus Chriſt. It is by one of them laid to our charge, as a great crime, that we alſo have not follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them in this Renunciation. This he ſaies,
<note place="margin">M <hi>Bart Model.</hi> p 119, 120.</note> 
               <hi>As learned and godly as the most and best of the Miniſters are, in the Church of</hi> England, <hi>yet (with grief of heart let it be ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken) very few of them have learned to this very day to diſclaim and renounce the evill and errour of the way of co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming into the Miniſtry, I mean, their Antichristian Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination, received from the Prelates,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Thoſe Biſhops be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Antichristian, their Ordination alſo muſt needs be ſo,</hi> &amp;c.] To which I ſay theſe things. 1. I deſire him
<pb facs="tcp:171559:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>to remember his own diſtinction;
<note place="margin">Pag. 80.</note> [<hi>We must distinguiſh between the corruption of things, and the things themſelves, between the eſsentials of a Church-ſtate, and the accidentals: Now it cannot be denied, but in reſpect of the Accidentals of a Church-ſtate, ſo all is loſt under the defection of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt, that is, in reſpect of the right order and adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Miniſtry, Ordinances, and Government: but not the eſſentials of theſe; and ſo long as theſe remain, the Church-ſtate is not lost,</hi> &amp;c.] Our Ordination therefore, was not Antichriſtian, though it be granted, that the Title and Office of a Dioceſan Biſhop, were Antichri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian: Nay, he ſeems to ſay and hold, that in <hi>Rome</hi> it ſelf, the Church-ſtate is not loſt, ſo long as the eſſenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als remain; <hi>viderit ipſe:</hi> But we ſay, The Prelates were certainly Presbyters, and ordained not alone, but toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, with the hands of a Presbytery: And if they did arrogate ſuch power to themſelves, as that no Ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion could paſſe without them; yet that was but an Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditional corrupt circumſtance; And himſelf tels us; <hi>[That the corruption of Adminiſtration doth not wholly make it null or void;]</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pag. 10.5.</note> Then (we ſay again) Our Ordination was not Antichriſtian; that which was ſo (if any thing in it was ſo) was rather the errour of the Ordainers, then of the Ordination, or ordained. 2. If the call of our Congregations will give us a right Ordination, moſt of us, if not all, have that to ſhew, as well as themſelves: A call or conſent of our people either explicit or impli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cit; which is confeſſed ſufficient, by the Reverend Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veyor of Church-Diſcipline,
<note place="margin">Par. 1. pag. 47. <hi>Thus the people and pariſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> &amp;c.</note> and acknowledged to be in our Churches; why then ſhould we renounce our Ordination? 3. If it be neceſſary to renounce our Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination as Antichriſtian, becauſe of a corruption in the Ordainers; I would ask him, whether Baptiſm ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtred
<pb facs="tcp:171559:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>(I ſay not by a Romiſh Prieſt) by a Miniſter ſo ordained, be not alſo Antichriſtian? (as Anabaptiſts do ſometimes object.) And whether he himſelf did ever to this day renounce and diſclaim his Baptiſm (like e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough done with the Sign of the croſſe, by ſome prela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tical Miniſter) as Antichriſtian? Himſelf propounds a like Queſtion thus: <hi>[Are not thoſe that we judge godly,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Modell,</hi> p. 105.</note> 
               <hi>and in a capacity to make uſe of all the holy Ordinances of Worſhip, to be baptized again?]</hi> And he anſwers nega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively, they are not, for this reaſon amongſt others. [<hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is ſuppoſed they have been (though corruptly) bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed already; Now the corruption of any adminiſtration, doth not wholly make it void and null, if they had the eſsen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tials of that Ordinance,</hi> &amp;c.] He might have been as fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourable to our Ordination, if he had pleaſed: But he may remember and ſatisfie another Query propounded by himſelf, to ſome Anabaptiſts, to be ſeriouſly conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered: <hi>[Whether there be any lawfull Baptiſm,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pag. 71.</note> 
               <hi>where the Adminiſtratour hath no lawfull calling thereunto?]</hi> And I would propound it, as ſeriouſly to be conſidered by him; Whether if our Ordination be (as he makes it) Antichriſtian, the Adminiſtratour of his Baptiſm, had any lawfull calling thereunto, and conſequently whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther his Baptiſm be lawfull or null; and he muſt not be rebaptized? And thereby gratifie the Anabaptiſts, as in others, ſo in this opinion and practice. But I proceed to another.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Their preaching as <hi>Gifted Brethren,</hi> (for ſo they only are to all Congregations but their own) hath cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed this generall liberty of preaching, by men not in Office, of all Trades and Profeſſions; to the contempt of the Miniſtry, to the multiplication of ſchiſms, divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, and ſeparations, from their former Miniſters and
<pb facs="tcp:171559:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>Churches; while every man hath liberty to propagate his own erroneous notions, and every man takes the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſe to hear whom he likes beſt, as moſt agreeable to his own opinion. Yea, this very Liberty taken and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed by them, hath almoſt brought as much contempt upon themſelves, as on the Presbyterian Miniſters; Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of their followers chuſing rather to hear even Boy-preachers, then themſelves.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Their placing all power in a particular Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation independently, without any power of appeal, makes an unjuſt cenſure irremedible. For this <hi>New-Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> it ſelf affords us a freſh and ſad inſtance, upon the report of very credible perſons. There was an Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication paſſed by the major part of a Congregation there, againſt a perſon who thought himſelf wronged, and deſired his cauſe to be heard, by the Elders of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Churches: who, upon the hearing doubted whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Excommunication could be juſtified. And they deſired the rehearing of it. But it would not be grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by that Congregation, or prevailing party in it: whereupon one of the Elders a reverend Paſtor of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Congregation, writes thus to a friend: [<hi>It will be a trouble to poor M.</hi> Ch. <hi>not to have his buſineſſe examined: but he muſt conſider how the caſe is, and look up to heaven, for I can aſſure him there is no help to be had upon earth, till the Churches are reformed, and become Presbyterian. I ſpeak ſeriouſly, I think that ſuch things will make ſome incline to the Presbyterian way, who formerly have been as firm In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dependents as M.—If Independency do not break all the Churches in</hi> New-England, <hi>except a few Semi-presbyteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, Some are deceived,</hi> &amp;c.] In conſideration whereof, he gives his adviſe, to divers other Independent Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, to think ſeriouſly of the Presbyterian way: and
<pb facs="tcp:171559:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>divers there, are become more moderate then formerly: Happy were it for <hi>Old England</hi> if our Diſſenting Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren would hearken betimes to this advice; before they have utterly broken their own and our Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches.</p>
            <p n="5">5. The power given to a Church-eſſentiall (as they call it) both to chuſe and ordain their own Officers, or Miniſters, as it is, and will be a cauſe of many factions and diviſions; ſo it will bring the Miniſters maintenance to depend upon the peoples benevolence; who may, and will upon the leaſt diſlike, reject him, and deny him any allowance; which will in a ſhort time deſtroy the Miniſtry, diſcourage others from the Miniſteriall cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, and conſequently ruine Religion. I have ſeen a Letter from <hi>New-England</hi> to this purpoſe; wherein ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſing his friend to do his endeavour to preſerve the ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed maintenance of the Miniſtry here; He ſaies, concerning <hi>New-England</hi> Miniſters thus: <hi>Though moſt of the people here grow wealthy, yet not one Miniſter almost, hath from the people a competency to maintain himſelf and family, except he have an eſtate of his own:</hi>] One main de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign of the Anabaptiſts or Jeſuites, in crying down Tithes here, is to deſtroy both Miniſtry at preſent, and Learning for the time to come, when there ſhall be no certain eſtabliſhment of a ſubſiſtence in that calling. How far our brethren have been aſſiſtant to this deſign, I wiſh them ſeriouſly to conſider.</p>
            <p n="6">6. It is the obſervation of many both learned and godly, That many of thoſe that once decline from us to the Independent way, ſtay not long with them, but fall preſently into Anabaptiſm, from thence to Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſm, from thence to Rantiſm, even the utmoſt of blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy and prophaneneſſe: Some poor ſouls have tired
<pb facs="tcp:171559:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>themſelves in ſeeking and trying all the New waies of Religion, and after a weary vagary to finde the truth, which they loſt, have returned home by weeping croſſe. But few there are that do ſo; which is a Lamentation, and ſhall be for a Lamentation. Yea, it is obſerved, that thoſe that run not into thoſe extremities of errours, blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy and prophaneſſe; yet fall ſtrangely from the power and practice of godlineſſe, wherein ſometimes they walked, and grow more remiſſe and looſe, in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret and family duties, in ſanctification of the Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> of which many holy men in former times and later, have found and ſaid, <hi>[That it was the Nurſe of ſo much piety in Old England, and the glory of our Church and Nation:]</hi> Little did we think, that thoſe who out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood the Sabbaticall profanations of the Prelates, their reproaches and ſcoffs of purity, preciſeneſſe and ſtrict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe (as they called it) would have ſo ſoon declined to the ſame looſeneſſe with them, upon a new pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed principle of Chriſtian Liberty, or Liberty of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience. But we ſee that to be true; <hi>[That the Sun (of Toleration) can do that with a Traveller, to make him caſt aſide his garment, which the stormy windes (of perſecution) could not do.]</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">7. And laſtly, To adde no more, Thoſe ſad and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver enough to be lamented Diviſions, in Towns, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations and Families; thoſe animoſities, jealouſies, bitterneſſes, heart-burnings, amongſt brethren; attend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with ſo much contempt and ſcorn of thoſe Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es and brethren, they have forſaken; being the fruits of this New Way; make it more then probable, this way is not the way of Chriſt. It is obſervable, that as ſoon as ever any begin to decline from us, though they were the entireſt boſome friends before, <hi>[ſuch as took ſweet
<pb facs="tcp:171559:8"/>counſel together, walking to the Houſe of God together as friends:]</hi> faſting and praying together often, in publike and private; communicating at the ſame Table of the Lord, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> after all this, they firſt withdraw and eſtrange themſelves, then come to ſlight both us, our Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and Miniſtry, as well as our perſons: and in ſome it ends in an open or ſecret oppoſition, and it's to be feared at laſt it will end in hotteſt perſecution. The Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Chriſt is a ſpirit of meekneſſe, gentleneſſe, and forbearance: The way of Chriſt, and the <hi>wiſedom which is from above, is first pure, then peaceable, gentle, eaſie to be entreated,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Theſe conſiderations of the evil fruits of the Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendent way (ſo called) I doe not therefore exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plifie (God is witneſſe) to caſt reproach upon the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of any of that way, who are (as I truſt, many are) truly godly, but only to give them occaſion ſeriouſly to review the principles by which they walk. And I would humbly entreat them to reade the following diſcourſes, without prejudice or partiality; and then judge, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther there be not a Diſcovery made of the weakneſſe of the foundation of their way: And if it prove ſo to be, to retract what they have more weakly built upon it, for the glory of God, and the peace of the Churches.</p>
            <p>If any ſay, you have ſaid much againſt their way, but nothing, or little, for the goodneſſe of the Presbyterian way. I anſwer, Enough hath been ſaid for it already, by the <hi>London</hi> Divines, in their <hi>Jus Divinum Regiminis Eccleſiaſtici;</hi> and the <hi>Vindication of the Presbyterian Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment</hi> by the Province there: This to me is a very probable argument of the goodneſſe of the Presbyteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an way, That all ſorts of men, Athieſts, Papiſts, Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copal, Anabaptiſts, all Sectaries, and prophane men
<pb facs="tcp:171559:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>do ſo much oppoſe it. That way (ſaid he) muſt needs be good, that <hi>Nero</hi> perſecutes: whereas moſt of theſe, the latter eſpecially like well of, and comply with the Independent way, as granting more Liberty then the Presbyterian will. Beſides that, the fruits of the Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterian Government, in other Reformed Churches, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially in the preventing or ſuppreſſing of errours, he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſies, and profaneſſe, ſpeaks ſufficiently for it.</p>
            <p>I had alſo ſome thoughts, to have vindicated the Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterian government from thoſe unjuſt aſperſions caſt upon it by M. <hi>B.</hi> in his Model, <hi>p.</hi> 52. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but they are ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſo weak or ſo falſe, that they fall by their own weight before an indifferent and intelligent Reader. I ſhall now ſtay the Reader no longer in the porch, but referre him to the Tracts themſelves: Deſiring the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting Brethren with ſingle and impartiall Judgements to conſider the miſerable rents and diviſions, the errors, hereſies and blaſphemies broken out in this Church of <hi>England,</hi> ſince their way got footing and countenance here: and withall (in the fear of God) to ſtudy how they may be repairers of thoſe breaches made, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorers of Truth and Peace loſt, to this diſtracted and almoſt deſtroied Church, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:171559:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>To the Preface.</head>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Authour of</hi> Vind. Clav. <hi>did not therefore con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceal his name, that he might ſecretly accuſe whom he durst not openly charge; but for other reaſons made known to, and approved of by Reverend and godly Brethren here. Nor was there any need (af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Roman cuſtom) for him to ſhew himſelf face to face; eſpecially when he charged nothing clanicular, but what he found, and any might finde publikely in the Authours own books. And had not the Subject and Titles of his books diſcovered him, he did not ſo much as name him in all his book, but only the firſt letters of his name: except once by citing the words of the Prefacers to</hi> The Way, <hi>in their Epistle. Love (it is true) is the beſt way to heal diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentions; but it is rather love of the Truth, then of mens perſons, if thoſe muſt be ſevered. And this the Authour of</hi> Vind. Clav. <hi>thought he manifeſted, in his vindication of it from thoſe errours and contradictions, which he found (as he ſtill thinks) in thoſe books he undertook. Yea, he thought he could not better ſhew his love to the Reverend Authour, then by manifesting his errours; as well as the weakneſſes of that way, wherein he is a Leader to many (ſuch is the reſpect to his perſon) beſides the way of Truth.</hi> Amicus Plato, <hi>&amp;c. And whoſe books do moſt</hi> breathe luſt to contention, <hi>his, who diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covers errours, or theirs, who defend them, being diſcovered; is left to the judgement of all indifferent Readers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>There is no doubt but the name of the Authour of</hi> Vind. Clav. <hi>is well enough known, to this Reverend Brother, by information of ſome from hence. He is one, who is known to honour and reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence his perſon, worth, and holineſſe, as much as any man; and as ſorry to ſee him ſo miſtake his way. One he is, that came to the read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb facs="tcp:171559:10"/>of his books, with praier and ſincerity, to finde, and ſubmit to the Truth found;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gal. 2.14.</note> 
               <hi>But when he ſaw, that he</hi> [walked not upright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly according to the Truth of the Goſpel,] <hi>he thought it his duty to withſtand him (as</hi> Paul <hi>did</hi> Peter) <hi>and to vindicate the Truth ſuppreſſed, and the Keys uſurped into the hands of the right owners. And that is the proper ſenſe of the word</hi> Vindiciae: <hi>The Aſſertion of Liberty or Freedom for the oppreſſed. It was not therefore an ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument of much love, to take the word in the worſer part, and to call the Authour by the name of</hi> vindex, <hi>(which ſometimes alſo ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies a</hi> Redreſſour <hi>of things, or a</hi> Defender <hi>or</hi> Reſtorer <hi>of Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty) much leſſe the</hi> Avenger: <hi>as if</hi> [the title and purport of the Book did hold him forth to be a man of Revenge:] <hi>For as there was no reaſon (no former difference being between them) ſo there ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears no footſtep of Revenge, in all his diſcourſe. The purport of the book, was not to revenge himſelf, but to vindicate, that is, to reſcue Truth, which he thought he ſaw oppreſſed, not ſo much by the ſtrength of Reaſon, as by the Authority of men in reputation for learning and holineſſe. And he thinks, (and ſo do others with him) there is more appearance of Revenge in the names of</hi> Vindex <hi>and</hi> Avenger <hi>put upon him unjuſtly (beſides the ſlighting of him in the ſhortneſſe of the Reply, of which more hereafter) then is to be found in all his proceedings. If there be any phraſe or paſſage too ſharp, or unbeſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the gravity of either party (as he begs pardon for it, ſo) he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires it may be imputed to that zeal he bears to the Truth, and to the ſouls of many ſeduced into a miſchievous ſeparation, the conſequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces whereof are found to be ſo dangerous to this Church of</hi> England, <hi>as threatning its utter deſolation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>But what ſaies he to the charge (in the Title page) of weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes and contradictions?</hi> If <hi>(ſaies he)</hi> Chriſt may have any glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry by that, I ſhall willingly acknowledge that I am made up of weakneſſes and contradictions;] <hi>If thoſe had been charged up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his perſon, he had anſwered religiouſly: But if it be only intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed againſt his way, he anſwers nothing: Or if this were really con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed, it would be not only to the glory of Chriſt, but his own alſo. But if it be (as it rather appears to be, by his Defence of thoſe weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes and contradictions) only modeſtly spoken, as intimating the contrary, ſurely Chriſt ſhall have little glory from that, and him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf leſſe. There is a way to ſeek glory, by flying it, and that is, no
<pb facs="tcp:171559:10"/>glory, ſaies the wiſest of men. But when he applies that to his perſon which was ſpoken of his books, he does but elude the charge, and not anſwer it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. [Nevertheleſſe <hi>(ſaies he)</hi> all this will not argue that which the Avenger ſaith, He hath heard that I have often altered my judgement ſince I went to <hi>New-England,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>That tho</hi> Aſſertor <hi>(not the</hi> Avenger) <hi>hath heard ſo,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Par. 1. pag. 28.</note> 
               <hi>and that of ſome near and dear friends of his, is true; and he hath found, that another (whom he under takes) hath heard ſo too: But that he hath altered his judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and that to contradiction, in his two Tracts,</hi> The Keys, <hi>and</hi> The Way, Vindex, <hi>the</hi> Affertor, <hi>thinks he hath made to appear in</hi> Vind. Clav. <hi>beyond any reaſonable contradiction, and ſhall do more in this. Now when he ſaies,</hi> [He ſees by the firſt words of the Way, that the Publiſhers had not the Copy taken from him, but an imperfect Tranſcript:] <hi>he laies a foundation for the eluding of all, or ſome at leaſt of the objected miſtakes; by diſclaiming their Copy: But then he looſes this ground again, when he ſaies:</hi> [I do beleeve what the Publiſhers do report (and they had it from his own Letters, as they ſay,) That ſetting aſide ſome dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference in Logical terms, there is no material difference between the Keys and the Way, either in doctrine of Divinity or Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>practice;] <hi>which is to own the Differences and Contradictions between thoſe Tracts, if any ſuch be proved: Of which in the next.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>It was objected, that the Authour of thoſe Tracts, did as flatly centradict himſelf, as ever any man did: For in the Keys he ſaith,</hi> [The Keys were delivered to <hi>Peter,</hi> as an Apoſtle,
<note place="margin">Pag. 4. Pag. 27.</note> as an Elder, and as a Beleever;] <hi>But in the Way, he ſaith,</hi> [They are given to <hi>Peter,</hi> not as an Apoſtle, not as an Elder, but as a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt Beleever:] <hi>Is not this a flat contradiction? There is a three<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold anſwer given to this Objection.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. The words <hi>(ſaies he)</hi> are not mine, but the Aſſertors,] <hi>The words as they are contracted are not his</hi> in terminis, <hi>but if they be not his, in their ſenſe, let Reaſon judge: In the</hi> Keys, <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounding the ſenſe of thoſe words,</hi> [To thee will I give the Keys, <hi>&amp;c.] he ſaies,</hi> [It hath proved a buſie Queſtion, How <hi>Peter</hi> is to be conſidered in receiving the power of the Keys; whether as an Apoſtle, or as an Elder, or as a Beleever: Now becauſe
<pb facs="tcp:171559:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>we are as well ſtudious of peace as of truth, we will not lean to one of theſe interpretations more then to another: (To ſpeak ingenuouſly and without offence what we conceive,) the ſenſe of the words will be moſt full, if all the ſeveral conſiderations be taken jointly together: Take <hi>Peter</hi> conſidered, not as an A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle only, but an Elder alſo, and a Beleever too, all may well ſtand together:] <hi>Does not this Diſcourſe clearly hold forth this Propoſition, as the ſenſe of that Text, The Keys were delivered to</hi> Peter <hi>as an Apoſtle, as an Elder, and as a Beleever too? (all may well stand together.)</hi>
               <note place="margin">See Keys pag. 5 If <hi>Peter</hi> then received the whole power of the Keys, then he ſtood in the room of all ſuch as have received any part of the power, Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, or El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, or Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches.</note> 
               <hi>And now take the words of the Way;</hi> [In the Goſpel of Chriſt, the power of the Keys is given to <hi>Peter,</hi> not as an Apoſtle, nor as an Elder, but as a profeſt Beleever:] <hi>And is not this a flat contradiction? <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>and that as ever man spake? (for contradictions do not</hi> recipere magis &amp; minus:) <hi>Yea, this latter propoſition is again contradicted, in this very Defence, when</hi> par. 2. p. 22. <hi>he ſaies,</hi> [<hi>Peter</hi> in his loweſt relation in the Church, (as a profeſt beleever) had his ſhare in the power of the Keys; not that he had his ſhare in the whole power of the Keys, as a profeſt Beleever: but that he had other parts of the power of the Keys, as an Elder, and as an Apoſtle, immediatly given him by the Lord Jeſus.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Now let any Logician judge, whether this be not as much as to ſay,</hi> [Peter had the power of the Keys given him as an Apoſtle, as an Elder, and as a Beleever: which is a flat contradiction to the other; The power of the Keys is given to <hi>Peter,</hi> not as an Apoſtle, not as an Elder, but as a profeſt beleever:] <hi>His Apolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy makes it worſe,</hi> [It is <hi>(ſaies he)</hi> a trivial rudiment in Schools, whatſoever is attributed to any as ſuch, is given to all as ſuch u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niverſally, reciprocally, and only; If the Keys were given to <hi>Peter</hi> as an Apoſtle, then to all the Apoſtles, and only to the Apoſtles:] <hi>Now aſſume; But the Keys were given to</hi> Peter <hi>as an Apoſtle, (ſaies he in the Keys) therefore they were given only to Apoſtles; and ſo not to beleevers as ſuch: Again, argue thus: If the Keys were given to</hi> Peter, <hi>not as an Apostle, not as an Elder, but as a Beleever, then to all Beleevers, and only to Beleevers: But (ſaies the Way) the Keys were not given to</hi> Peter <hi>as an Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, nor as an Elder, therefore they were given to all Beleevers (women and all) and only to Beleevers. What the Publiſhers of
<pb facs="tcp:171559:11"/>the</hi> Keys <hi>ſay, helps not off the contradiction at all;</hi> [The diſpoſal <hi>(ſay they)</hi> of this power may lie in a due allotment into divers hands, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> rather then in an entire and ſole Truſt, to one man, or any ſort or rank of men or Officers:] <hi>For they agree not with their Authour, nor he with them: He ſaies, this power of the Keys is given only to Beleevers: They ſay, it is put into divers hands: and is not this a contradiction? But he takes himſelf wronged by the Aſſertor, affirming him to place all the power in one ſort of men, in that place;</hi> The Way, <hi>pag.</hi> 45. <hi>which in the ſame paſſage he does deny,</hi> [They <hi>(the brethren)</hi> may not adminiſter Sacraments in defect of all Officers;] <hi>Truly this is to diſcover the contradiction more: For if the Keys be delivered to beleevers only as ſuch, then the power of adminiſtring Sacraments is given to them: for that is a part of the power of the Keys: But he aſſerts the former in the</hi> Way, <hi>pag.</hi> 27. <hi>therefore, Take his own Propoſition, or argument,</hi> a quatenus tale; [If <hi>Peter</hi> had received the power of the Keys, <hi>quatenus Apoſtulus,</hi> or <hi>quatenus Presbyter,</hi> then only Apoſtles, or only Elders had received all Church-power:] <hi>Does it not follow as well, If</hi> Peter <hi>received the power of the Keys,</hi> quatenus <hi>a Beleever, then only Beleevers had received all Church-power? But</hi> Peter <hi>received the power of the Keys,</hi> quatenus <hi>a Beleever, (not as an Apoſtle, nor as an Elder) ſaies he expreſly,</hi> The Way, <hi>p.</hi> 27. <hi>Therefore only beleevers have received all Church-power. And if all Church-power, then of adminiſtring Sacraments, which he af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter denies: Beſides, in the place named</hi> (the Way, <hi>pag.</hi> 45.) <hi>he gives the brethren the greater part of Church-power,</hi> viz. <hi>to or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain and excommunicate all their Officers: which are the highest Acts of Rule (as he elſewhere ſpeaks) therefore he may not deny them the leſſer to adminiſter Sacraments: Yet he ſaies,</hi> [He that ſaith, <hi>Peter</hi> received the power of the Keys, as in the room of all ſorts of Officers and members, he affirmeth that <hi>Peter</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived all Church-power, found in Beleevers, Officers, or Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren: And is there any paſſage in the Keys, which croſſeth or contradicteth this?] <hi>The Aſſertor did not ſay there was any paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage in the Keys, that contradicts this; but he ſtill ſaies (as then he ſaid) there is a paſſage in the</hi> Way, <hi>that not only croſſes, but contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicts this, and that flatly, as never man more; Thus, he that ſaies,</hi> Peter <hi>received the Keys, not as an Apoſtle, nor as an Elder, but
<pb facs="tcp:171559:12"/>(that is, only) as a Beleever, contradicts that: as now is evident to any eye,</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>But a ſecond anſwer is given to help out the firſt:</hi> [If there had been ſome difference between the Way and the Keys, in ſome expreſſions; yet (as the Praefacers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>) it lay rather in Logical terms, then in doctrine, or Church-practice, and ſuch is this, about the firſt ſubject of the power of the Keys, <hi>&amp;c.] Had it been only a leſſer difference about a Logicall notion (as he minces it) the Aſſertor had not obſerved it: but a difference (of the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt magnitude) to contradiction, in delivering a</hi> new way, <hi>is very remarkable: How ſhall we be brought to agree with them that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradict not only one another, but one man himſelf?</hi> 2. <hi>The firſt ſubject is indeed a Logicall term, but the matter diſcourſed is do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrinall Divinity; and whatever the practice be, it is in Divinity as well as in Logick, a contradiction to ſay, The Keys were given to</hi> Peter <hi>as a Beleever only, and to</hi> Peter <hi>as an Apoſtle and Elder too: To ſay, all the power of the Keys is given to the Brethren, as Beleevers; and yet to ſay, The power of adminiſtring Sacraments is not given to them. And if the practice be not ſutable to the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, it makes yet a more remarkable difference: why this is alſo told us,</hi> The Way, <hi>p.</hi> 45. [They <hi>(the brethren)</hi> might proceed againſt all Officers as well as one, yet in ſuch caſes our Churches are never wont to proceed, but in the preſence, and with the conſent and approbation of other Churches:] <hi>But then their Doctrine and practice agree not, which is the greater blemiſh, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing they hold that power of the Church to be</hi> jure divino, <hi>and imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatly from Chriſt: And as for adminiſtration of Sacraments, and preaching the Word ordinarily, we know not what you practiſe in</hi> New-England; <hi>but we are ſure in</hi> Old-England, <hi>They that were never Evangelically ordained (or have renounced their Ordinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) do both preach and administer Sacraments; and ſo doctrine and practice contradict one another.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>There is yet a third anſwer to ſuccour both the former<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> [It were no juſt matter of calumny, if in fome latter Tractate I ſhould retract or expreſſe more commodiouſly what I wrote in a former leſſe ſafely: as <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> &amp;c.] <hi>Truly Sir, it had been no juſt mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of calumny ſo to do; but of honour and reputation rather. But to write contradictions, and to take no notice of them, till obſerved by
<pb facs="tcp:171559:12"/>others; and then to be ſo far from retracting, as to ſtand upon juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication of them, is nothing like S.</hi> Auguſtines <hi>practice, and ſo fals ſhort of his reputation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>There are in that Epiſtle Praefatory, as alſo in the Animadverſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons upon the Epiſtle to the Keys, other differences obſerved, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween their Authour and the Praefacers; but he is not pleaſed to take notice of them; It is too hard perhaps to reconcile others with him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf: It is well if he can reconcile himſelf to himſelf: which how, and how far he is pleaſed to do, we now follow him to conſider.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:171559:13"/>
            <head>Errata.</head>
            <p>PAge 5. line 10. for <hi>on</hi> reade <hi>or.</hi> p. 9. l. 15. for <hi>not</hi> r. <hi>yet.</hi> and put in <hi>be</hi> in the end of the line. p. 11. l. 17. for <hi>ſent</hi> r. <hi>ſhut.</hi> p. 12. l. 29. for <hi>declared</hi> r. <hi>enlar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged.</hi> p. 24. in marg. for 7. r. 3. p. 34. l. 3. after <hi>elſe</hi> put in <hi>then but.</hi> p. 37. l. 12. for <hi>effect</hi> r. <hi>affect.</hi> Ibid l. 28. for <hi>wickedneſses</hi> r. <hi>weakneſſes.</hi> p. 38. l. 3. for <hi>new</hi> r. <hi>now.</hi> p. 40. ſect. 1. for <hi>fill</hi> r. <hi>full.</hi> p. 53. l. 1. for <hi>Criticall</hi> r. <hi>Crypticall.</hi> p. 72. l. 8. for <hi>Congregation</hi> r. <hi>Corporation.</hi> p. 77. l. 34. for <hi>promiſes</hi> r. <hi>premiſes.</hi> p. 83. l. 27. for <hi>oratio</hi> r. <hi>operatio.</hi> p. 89. l. 31. for <hi>if</hi> r. <hi>is.</hi> p. 93. l. 15. r. <hi>his meaning and theirs to be as.</hi> p. 97. l. 14. for <hi>precious</hi> r. <hi>previous.</hi> p. 104. l. 3. for <hi>conſideration</hi> r. <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federation.</hi> p. 106. l. 27. for <hi>both</hi> r. <hi>but.</hi> p. 121. l. 1. for <hi>entruſted</hi> r. <hi>intereſted.</hi> p. 125. l. 1. after <hi>before,</hi> put in, <hi>us.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
